Guide to the Hudson-Fulton Celebration collection CBHM.0034
Center for Brooklyn History
Hudson-Fulton Celebration collection
1909-1910
Center for Brooklyn History
CBHM.0034
0.25 Linear feet in one manuscript box and one oversize folder.
Publications, ephemera and photographs from the 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration in New York City and elsewhere along the Hudson River.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The napkin was the gift of Harriet Stryker-Rodda, 1974. The photographs were the gift of Gerard W.B. Gardner, 1981. The sources and dates of acquisition for the remainder of the collection are unknown.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged into 14 folders by type.
Historical note
The Hudson-Fulton Celebration was a two week event held in September and October of 1909 commemorating both the 300th anniversary of Henry Hudson's arrival at what we now call the Hudson River and the 100th anniversary of Robert Fulton's first successful run of his steamboat service between New York City and Albany, N.Y. Events held during the celebration included parades, fireworks, concerts, exhibitions, and the illumination of the exteriors of various buildings, bridges, and monuments throughout New York City with electric lights. Events took place throughout New York City, as well as in several cities located along the Hudson River. A major attraction of the Celebration was the participation of the U.S. Navy Atlantic Fleet. The main Brooklyn pageant began at the Soldiers and Sailors' Memorial Arch in Grand Army Plaza and continued on Eastern Parkway to Buffalo Avenue.
Scope and Contents
Publications, ephemera and photographs from the 1909 Hudson-Fulton Celebration in New York City and elsewhere along the Hudson River. The publications include officially authorized publications as well as those published by the Celebration Commission itself. There are also programs and souvenir publications from other sources, such as the New York State Education Department, the Jersey City Free Public Library and the Fulton Trust Company.
There are three items specific to the festivities in Brooklyn: a calendar of events, a list of members on the Brooklyn Citizens' Committee, and a napkin from a Brooklyn event during the Celebration. Additionally, six photographs depict various structures around New York City (but mostly in Brooklyn) illuminated with electric lights in honor of the Celebration.
- Celebration Commission minutes and committtee list, June-July 1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Officially authorized publications, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Official Program, Carnival Pageant official souvenir booklet, and Historical Pageant program. Printed for the Commission by Redfield Brothers, Inc.
- Official commission announcements, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Schedule of events, medal, and badge announcement booklets.
- Hudson and Fulton by Edward Hagaman Hall, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Two copies, first edition and third edition. "A brief history of Henry Hudson and Robert Fulton with suggestions designed to aid the holding of general commemorative exercises and children's festivals during the Hudson-Fulton Celebration." Published by the Celebration Commission.
- Dedications: Programs and Historical Sketches, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  "Compiled and published by the Committee on Dedications for use of the Societies and Organizations dedicating memorials under the auspices of the…Celebration Commission."
- Information booklet, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  "Issued…by the Public Health and Convenience Committee of the…Celebration Commission."
- Texts on Fulton's Steamship Clermont, circa 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Issued by the Commission/George M. Moran.
- Testimonials of Appreciation to Herman Ridder and Henry W. Sackett, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Ridder and Sackett were the Acting President and Secretary, respectively, of the Celebration Commission.
- NYHS Robert Fulton exhibition catalogue, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Presented September 27-October 30 in cooperation with the Colonial Dames of America.
- New York Genealogical and Biographical Society exhibition catalogue, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Presented September 25-October 9.
- NYS Education Department booklet, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  "A brochure for the use of schools of the state compiled and edited by Harlan Hoyt Horner."
- Souvenir Book, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  By Louis F. Gautier, copyright Weber Publishing Co.
- Celebration program, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Copyright Necomb Publishing Co.
- Program for Hudson, NY, October 3-9, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Events included addresses by Rev. Newell Dwight Hillis and Rev. S. Parkes Cadman.
- Jersey City Free Public Library souvenir booklet and book list, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Compiled by Edmund W. Miller, Press of A.J. Doan.
- Hudson River by Daylight magazine Vol. XII No. 14, August 30, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes listings of concert programmes for steamers Hendrick Hudson, Robert Fulton, and Albany.
- Historical Explanation of the Dutch Floats booklet, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Issued by the Holland Hudson-Fulton Society of Albany and Vicinity.
- Life of Robert Fulton booklet, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Published by Fulton Trust Company of New York.
- Brooklyn Citizens' Committee list, circa 1909 (Box OS-25)
- Brooklyn Calendar, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Issued by the Brooklyn Citizens' Committee.
- Brooklyn celebration napkin, 1909; 1978.110 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Historical note
  The donor described her experience at the celebration in notes that accompany this item: "My sister Ruth and I were dressed in Japanese costumes and rode on the Japanese float in the section of the parade on 4th Avenue, Brooklyn, which originated at the Fourth Avenue Methodist Church...refreshments at the church consisted of tea, rice cakes, and other Japanese delicacies, with ice cream for the children."
  Paper napkin used at the refreshment period following the Hudson-Fulton Celebration in Brooklyn in 1909 and notes describing the celebration. The napkin depicts a Japanese garden, consistent with the Japanese theme of the gathering.
- Prints, circa 1909 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Images of official badge and Fort Tryon monument.
- Photographs, 1909; V1990.054 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Custodial History
  The donor, Gerard W.B. Gardner, received these as a gift from his aunt Mildred K. Bindrim circa 1941.
  Six black-and-white photographic prints showing various Brooklyn and Manhattan locations at night, and illuminated with electric lights, during the Hudson-Fulton Celebration of 1909. Five of the photographs show views of buildings and monuments in Brooklyn.
- Dutch clippings, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Based on their markings, these items are possibly from the files of the Brooklyn Eagle.
  Coverage of the Celebration and images of Henry Hudson's ship The Half Moon.